chapter 4 is called the generative
models of active inference and it begins
with a quotation everything should be
made as simple as possible but not
simpler by Albert Einstein Ali what is
your overview thought or
warning for chapter four
okay so uh after the preliminary
materials
um in chapters two and three uh which
was basically largely based on
um concept providing some conceptual
framework for developing uh the further
Theory chapter four delves into much
more detail in terms of mathematical
formulation and it unpacks a lot more uh
the way that the central equations of
active inference is derived and how to
construct
the important elements of active
inference models so say
matrices a b c and d and also how to put
together a generative models in
different situations so it basically
lays out the foundation or
um for I mean constructing an active
inference models uh both for discrete
time situations and continuous time at
once uh which will be used later in
chapters seven and eight but this is uh
probably one of the most uh challenging
and uh at least mathematically dense
chapters in the book so I would
personally suggest reading through this
chapter really slowly and even if we
don't get to understand every single
detail of the chapter uh obviously we
can return
required as we go through uh the
textbook
thank you Ali yes so let's look through
the sections just to add on though
chapter four is one of the larger and
more equation dense chapters because it
is the common kernel or basis that's
then going to get applied in chapter
five in the neurobiological case
there's a recipe for making chapter 4 in
chapter six that's the recipe for active
inference modeling chapter 7 and 8 are
about the discrete and the continuous
time variant or or subtype or motif of
these kinds of things called generative
models so this is the real common root
and
we'll just look at what the sections are
this chapter complements the preceding
chapters conceptual treatment of active
inference with a more formal treatment
section 4.2 from Bayesian inference to
free energy
what would you say about this
sectionally
okay so as we know the free energy
principle is inspired by previous work
on Bayesian inference I mean all the way
way back to
helmholtz theory about
um
unconscious inference or something to
that effect I can remember the exact
term but here
um I mean
it provides in a more in a bit more
detail how we can derive pre-energy
principle uh formalism using the
established Bayesian inference
formulation
and particularly one of the key
uh movements or at least one of the key
decisions uh in uh through the
derivation of free energy principle
formulation is using uh Jane's
inequality principle to derive uh
an upper upper bound instead of just
using uh the exact values to compute
um or or to achieve required parameters
so uh that's basically uh
in my opinion the key premise of uh
section 4.2
and to see uh in a bit more detail how
we can achieve those uh upper bounds
using uh Jane's inequality uh directly
from by using
um
I mean manipulations of Bayesian
inference
based in statistical formalism
thanks I'll just add one point from this
section broadly these are the problems
of inferring states of the world
perception and inferring a course of
action planning so this is again
referring to the perception and action
and everything that happens in between
is the internal or the cognitive part of
the inference but this is like the
blanket State cybernetic input output
and then
let's look at the first equation or how
much equations overall or what equations
do you think we should highlight
uh okay so
um maybe we can uh I mean uh just uh as
a general comment about these um
different equations uh well each of
these equations provide a distinct step
toward deriving uh the ultimate whole
picture so uh even if we don't quite
understand how we can derive from uh
each step to the other one
it's good to know that
it's only required to understand how we
get to that ultimate whole picture but
ultimately what we would need in order
to develop
um for a develop active inference models
is the ultimate equation or ultimate
whole picture so this is just
um
a way to elucidate uh the steps toward
developing uh that whole picture but
um again it's not an essential
requirement to understand
um the materials of the rest of the book
uh but if we go from uh I mean equations
4.1 toward the 4.4 or other words the
free A variation of free energy well
equation 4.1 is just a basic definition
of
um probably
some properties of probabilities
in terms of conditional probability and
so on so equation 4.2 provides the
central
chains inequality principle and how it
relates to
um I mean conditional probabilities and
uh of course joint probabilities and
then by using uh those uh two properties
or those two equations we ultimately get
to 4.4 which is the definition of
variation free energy parameter uh which
is the parameter of interest that needs
to be optimized in order to inference to
happen
or at least perceptual inference to
happen in active inference models
thanks only thing all add is f is the
letter used for variational free energy
you can think of it like a computer
program and the arguments that it takes
in or the variables that it takes in are
Q which is the distribution that's under
the statisticians control and Y which
are the data which are outside of the
statisticians control
and
do you want to describe more about
anything
in this equation or carry on
uh just one thing to uh that can
probably be helpful is to somehow
compare these steps with
um the initial picture we had from uh
chapter two uh because uh variation of
free energy was first introduced in
chapter two so uh it can be helpful to
go back and forth between chapters two
and four and try to connect the dots
between
um the related points there
section 4.3 generative models
all right I'll read the first sentence
then you can give some thoughts
to calculate the for the free energy
we need three things data a family a
variational distributions and a
generative Model comprising A prior and
a likelihood
in this section we outline two very
general sorts of generative model used
for active inference and the form the
free energy takes in relation to each
but
okay so uh as mentioned earlier this
chapter deals both with discrete time
and continuous time situations uh so
clearly we would need two different
types of generative models for each
situation
and
obviously the the generative models or
the way to construct generative models
for discrete time situations uh would
vary quite a bit from uh the one for
continuous time situations
but the general principle underlying uh
those generative models are basically
the same which is uh I mean to somehow
construct a model of the environment and
I mean either be it
for the situation that that is
sequential in time or for the situations
that need to be somehow
each moment of the situation needs to be
accommodated in terms of a continuous
time situation so uh
figure 4.2 provides some examples of
both so
for uh yes let me see
yes so we have some examples of
different kinds of generative models
some uh case case studies if you like
and it provides various ways to show how
the the dependencies between between
variables can be modeled using
these kinds of graphical probabilistic
models so one common way to represent
General to models is to use these kinds
of graphical
probabilistic models in active imprints
literature which is at least in this
case the circles would represent the
random variables and the squares
that would represent the distributions
which would describe
the dependencies between those random
variables
so we can see uh the clear relationships
between those parameters here which is
basically what this whole graph what
constitutes the generative model that
needs to be used for different
situations and then in figure 4.3
we can compare
the two different types of generative
models based on uh whether it's discrete
time or continuous time situations so
the upper picture is a generative model
for the discrete time situation and the
lower picture
is the parallel continuous time version
of it and as we can see the general
topology of these models are the same
the only things that differ is the use
of parameters for
policies or I mean discrete time
policies or the continuous templates and
we can obviously compare the different
elements for for both uh priors States
and
external States internal States and so
on by comparing these two models here
yeah we often return to figure 4.3 it's
kind of the Rosetta Stone
of generative modeling for the context
of this book because it's then going to
develop out into chapter seven and eight
and it represents a really fundamental
decision made in modeling
and
in the later chapters it's also shown
how it can be made into a hierarchical
model that combines aspects of both
but within each level of modeling still
these are the kinds of decisions that
modelers are presented with when it
comes to statistical modeling overall
so section 4.4 goes into essentially the
top half of figure 4.3 discrete time
what would you say about discrete time
okay so uh the discrete time situation
uh is uh obviously the archetype
discrete time situation which is upon
the Palm DP models so at this point I
would very much like to recommend uh
following uh the steps following the
material from step by step paper because
uh that's uh in that paper uh the way to
construct pump DP models is described in
a bit more detail so if anyone feels
like they should learn a bit more about
the the gaps in the details uh I I would
very much like to recommend that
particular paper so
uh yeah uh I don't know how much detail
uh we should go into because uh it's I
mean uh although uh it's not maybe a
detailed enough for some tastes but it
goes in a quite uh extensive detail uh
about how we can construct these models
using the the concepts we've learned uh
in previous chapters uh so
ultimately we reach equations
4.13 and
4.14 which are basically the culmination
of palm DP formulation using the vector
notations and gradients and so on so
uh
that's great and we go to continuous
time situation
great
few things intervene in the continuous
time
chapter ones that we'll just mention
here because they're kind of boxed or
partitioned from The Continuous time
part but they're following Pages first
is Markov blankets we won't go into it
here but kind of footnote that or look
at some other places where we talk about
it outside of this chapter overview
figure 4.4 AZ message passing
again a big topic
let's kind of just go past it now
back to the regularly scheduled
continuous time generative model
discussion
and then another box to the generalized
coordinates of motion
so taking position plus derivatives of
position
and that has some beneficial properties
that are described and unpacked also
elsewhere
do you want to say anything about 4.5.2
uh well the only thing that comes to
mind is
although as I said before
all the formulations here may look uh
more I mean a bit too dense to
understand at the first pass but uh some
of the key
maybe components here
could be uh obviously the the material
from box 4.2 and 4.3 uh is uh I think
are quite essential to understand uh the
uh the underlying principle behind uh
deriving uh The Continuous time
situation because without LaPlace
approximation what we would have uh in
terms of free energy minimization is uh
it would look very much like the Gibbs
it gives free energy so uh I mean the
key distinction between uh
the free energy Principle as described
in active inference literature as
opposed to Gibbs free energy is this
distinction uh is the LaPlace
approximation so this is what enables us
to go from Gibbs free energy to
um I mean the variation of free energy
so uh yeah that's uh I mean quite
essential to uh make this to be familiar
with this essential approximation and
obviously the concept of generalized
coordinates of motion will come time and
time again throughout the whole book
particularly in chapters uh eight and
nine uh so yeah those two concepts I
believe
needs a bit more attention
so yeah sounds good box 4.3 LaPlace
approximation
equations
another message passing representation
and a summary
the key message to take away is that
approximate Bayesian inference may be
framed as minimizing a quantity
known as variational free energy this
depends on the generative model that
expresses our belief about how data are
generated anything else you want to add
ah nothing comes to mind at the moment
because as I said this is I mean we're
still
in the stage that we want to develop are
essential tools to be used in the rest
of the book so uh here up until now I
Believe by the end of chapter four we
have acquired all the essential
necessary mathematical tools and the
next chapter chapter 5 is kind of acts
like an interlude
and I don't think it's the direct
um I mean continuation of chapters uh
one through four so I believe the the
first
um section or the first part of the book
uh conceptually and mathematically ends
here so yeah that's it
yes it's a little bit like the pragmatic
modeling part gets foreshadowed or
explored in five now that we're all
built up with four all right that's the
end of the overview for four